Home to more than 50,000 people, South
Haven, Mississippi, is a quiet suburb.
That is, residents say, until Elon
Musk's AI power plant came to town.
For months now, this is the sound
communities near the plant hear.
All day
and night. It sounds like jets are
taking off and they never take off.
Coming from dozens of methane turbines
set to power Elon Musk's AI data center.
That's the power plant and we're getting
a decibel reading here in the low 60s.
That's about as loud as a dishwasher
running 24/7 just steps from that house.
When I was a little girl, the garden was
all right over there. Crystal Polk's
family has lived here for generations,
before black people were even allowed to
own property. What has life been like
for you since the turbines came to town?
Excruciating. The noise is constant and
never ends. This is the noise that we
are experiencing at 9:00 at night.
Sometimes it's very, very, very loud
with loud screeching and railing, like
rails are hitting up against each other.
It's just unbearable. And it's not just
a concern over noise, but air pollution,
too. Non-profit newsroom Floodlight
published this thermal drone footage,
which they say shows the gas burning at
the facility. The Environmental
Protection Agency has said gas turbines
are a major source of hazardous air
pollutants, including formaldehyde and
other probable human carcinogens. I have
severe asthma and sometimes I can smell
the pollution in the air and I don't
want to be exposed to that and cause
more damage to myself. The Mississippi
Department of Environmental Quality
telling NBC News right now they've
confirmed the facility is utilizing
efficient air pollution control
technology to minimize emission, despite
operating without an air permit for
months, which the department said wasn't
required for the initial temporary
turbines. We don't really know how bad
this pollutant is right now.
Jason Haley has doubts. Do you worry it
could be bad?
>> Yes, I do. You shouldn't put this right
next to people's neighborhoods. He
co-founded the Safe and Sound Coalition,
a group trying to stop those turbines
from becoming permanent. It's March 5th
at 12:10 a.m.
He says people like this officer come by
every few hours to take decibel
readings, but that the readings don't
tell the whole story. We took a decibel
reading down at the park and it was like
in the 50s, 60s, which is equivalent to
the hum of a dishwasher, which might not
sound like much to people.
>> I've heard the comparison to this isn't
much louder than my dishwasher or my
vacuum cleaner is louder than that.
Well, you don't run that 24/7. XAI did
not respond to NBC News's request for
comment about the Mississippi plant and
residents' concerns. South Haven's mayor
called the noise a legitimate concern
and says XAI installed a $7 million
sound wall and is considering more
mitigation. He also emphasized the
economic impact. Our city and entire
community will soon reap unprecedented
financial benefits from this new
strategic alliance. XAI plans to spend
more than $20 billion in the area, the
governor announced, bringing with it
much-needed jobs. But Jason and Crystal
are not alone in their worry. Hundreds
of people showed up to the state hearing
in South Haven, urging officials to
reject XAI's bid for 41 permanent gas
turbines. This month, Mississippi
regulators unanimously approved those
permanent turbines, which the
Mississippi Department of Environmental
Quality says will require an air permit.
On X, Elon Musk said he was thrilled it
was approved, adding it powers the
future of AI innovation. A future the
residents we spoke to say will cost them
their own.
>> I can't live with this. I'm going to
have to move. Tell me more about what's
happening to you right now.
It's just the thought that this might be
the end
of something that's been in my family
for years. And I feel like
we don't matter to those who are in
charge, that we are invisible to them.
Priscilla Thompson, NBC News, South
Haven, Mississippi.
We thank you for watching and remember
stay updated on breaking news and top
stories on the NBC News app or watch
live on our YouTube channel.